So we start on מ"ט עמוד א' Mem Tet Amud Aleph in
the משנה. Mishna. Hopefully we'll catch up on today.
And we still remember the overarching theme here is about אין מעכבין,
Ein Me'akvin, but now we're onto the world of קרבנות. Korbanot. So
we dealt within one קרבן, Korban, the very tight relationship between the
כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret and the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. And now
we move on to some other groups of קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay. התמידים
אין מעכבין את המוספים. Hatmiddim ein me'akvin et hamussafim. If you have
the תמיד Tamid but you don't have the מוסף Mussaf at שבת
Shabbos let's say, and you have two lambs, so you can use
them for תמידים Tmidim but you won't use them for מוספים. Mussafim.
You can still go ahead and bring the תמידים Tmidim without the
מוספים. Mussafim. ולא המוספים מעכבין את התמידים Velo hamussafim me'akvin et hatmidim
or if you have קרבנות Korbanot for מוספים Mussafim but not for
תמידים, Tmidim, they won't prevent you from bringing the—if bring you can
bring the מוסף Mussaf even if you won't be able to bring
the תמיד. Tamid. Okay. ולא
המוספים מעכבין זה את זה. Velo hamussafim me'akvin zeh et zeh. If
you don't have all the מוספים, Mussafim, right? There's usually a big
group of like one cow, two lambs or—two cows, one ram, seven
sheep or something. If you don't have all of them, then you
can bring some of them. Not only that, if you have multiple
מוספים, Mussafim, let's say it's שבת ראש חודש Shabbos Rosh Chodesh and
you have enough for one and not for the other, you're not—one
is not held back without the other. Wait, you mean the מוסף
Mussaf for שבת Shabbos aren't מעכב me'akev on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
or even like let's say you have one ram? Right, both. Right,
okay. Both. Okay.
לא, Lo, now it's going to say. לא הקריבו כבש בבוקר יקריבו
בין הערביים. Lo hikrivu keves baboker yakrivu bein haarbayim. If you don't
bring the lamb in the morning, you can still bring the one
in the afternoon. The two תמידים Tmidim are not מעכב me'akev one
another, which is interesting. You might have thought like make it a
pair, either do the whole thing or not. But it's similar by
the מוסף. Mussaf. You don't need the whole group, you bring what
you can—but אמר רבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says, אימתי? Eimatai? When is this true? בזמן שהיו אנוסים או שוגגים.
Bizman shehayu anusim o shogegim. If it's—you're not to blame, you were
אונס onus or you were שוגג, shogeg, somehow it was not like
a willful פשיעה. p'shaya. אבל אם היו מזידים, Aval im hayu mezidim,
if it was a willful פשיעה, p'shaya, ולא הקריבו כבש בבוקר velo
hikrivu keves baboker and they for some reason they didn't do it
in the morning, they said oh let's hold on to this, maybe
we'll use it for the מוסף Mussaf or whatever it might have
been, לא יקריבו בין הערביים, lo yakrivu bein haarbayim, they cannot bring
it in the afternoon. Now, he doesn't hold that for מוספין. Mussafin.
He doesn't hold that for מוספין Mussafin because—but I want to remind
you of another position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon from an earlier
משנה. Mishna. מסכת מנחות? Masechet Menachot? No, where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said that if you have to choose between doing some of the
מוספים, Mussafim, some of the animals with their נסכים, nesachim, or doing
all of them without their נסכים, nesachim, better to do a few—fewer
but do it right. Do some with their נסכים. nesachim. And there's
something similar I think in this position here, which is, he'd rather
you not do it at all than do it and do it—you
know, do it in a half-baked way. What? I like that idea.
Better never than late. Well, okay, so there, right. So here, it's
like don't do any of the תמידים Tmidim unless you're going to
do both. Okay, assuming don't make that your choice, right? That's the
מזידים. mezidim. Don't choose to do only one if you're not going
to do both. If you had no choice, maybe we'll let you
do it. The same way before he said don't choose to do
all of the מוספים Mussafim but do them poorly. What you're going
to do, do correctly. So the same way there there was a
relationship between each animal and its מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, which he
presumably held was a more of a relationship than between one animal
and the next. Here too he holds there's a relationship between the
two מנחות—between minchot the two תמידים. Tmidim. So either bring both תמידים
Tmidim or don't bring either, at least if it's your choice. If
you're an אונס, onus, that's a different story. Now the משנה Mishna
goes on. He because also says ואת הכבש השני, ve'et hakeves hasheni,
which implies that there's a כבש הראשון. keves harishon. Right, that's what
the—that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to talk—I understand. But the חכמים
Chachamim aren't, you know, persuaded by that. And I'm just pointing out
that he feels, you know, that you see with him, he wants
the things to come with what they're supposed to accompany them. And
even if it means that if you're not going to do it,
don't do it at all. Okay. Okay. לא הקטירו קטורת בבוקר יקטירו
בין הערביים. Lo hiktiru ktoret baboker yaktiru bein haarbayim.
If you don't bring the קטורת ktoret in the morning, you can
bring it in the afternoon, right? Half of the מנה maneh of
the קטורת ktoret was brought in the morning, half in the afternoon.
אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, now it's not clear whether רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would disagree with this or not, but here's what
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon right means—maybe he would say also you do
both or don't do either. But here's something else that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon said. אמר רבי שמעון וכולה הייתה קרבה בין הערביים. Amar
Rabbi Shimon vekula hayata kreva bein haarbayim.
When you would bring it in the afternoon, so he seems like
he's okay with making this choice, but if for some reason you—it's
not like you only had a half measure and you only bring
half in the afternoon. You had the full measure and some reason
you forgot to bring it in the morning. Then he's saying fine,
bring it in the afternoon, that I agree to, but then you
bring the full amount. Okay, you understand? Like you had a מנה,
maneh, whatever that was, a unit that was brought of this קטורת.
ktoret. Half in the morning, half in the afternoon. You missed your
morning. What are you going to do in the afternoon? So here
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, okay, I'll admit you can do the
afternoon without the morning. Why is the קטורת ktoret different? We'll see.
Maybe like Michael says, because by the two תמידים Tmidim it emphasizes
that they come as a pair. Maybe by the קטורת ktoret I
can do with just the afternoon. But even here רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says don't just bring half. If you're bringing it only in
the afternoon, bring the full amount in the afternoon. But if you
missed a day, you wouldn't like triple up or? No, no. Okay,
so we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. But he is going
to now—and now the משנה Mishna seems to again switch gears and
the גמרא's Gemara going to try to make sense of how these
people work together. שאין מתחנכת מזבח הזהב אלא בקטורת הסמים. She'ein mitchaneket
mizbach hazahav ela biktoret hasamim. The way you anoint the מזבח הזהב...
mizbach hazahav... Inaugurate the golden altar is with burning the קטורת. ktoret.
So if you just created a new golden altar, you would bring
the קטורת ktoret and that would inaugurate it. ולא מזבח העולה אלא
בתמיד של שחר, V'lo mizbeach ha-olah ela b'tamid shel shachar, and you
don't only bring the, you only inaugurate the altar, the, you know,
the outer altar with the morning תמיד. tamid. Now actually what the
גמרא Gemara is going to add is מחנכין את מזבח הזהב, mechanchin
et mizbeach hazahav, I think it says בקטורת הסמים של בין הערביים,
bi-ktoret hasamim shel bein ha-arbayim, if I remember correctly what the גמרא
Gemara says.
Anyway, we'll see it in the גמרא Gemara how this is how
this is at all relevant to the point we're just making. ולא
את השולחן אלא בלחם הפנים בשבת, V'lo et hashulchan ela b'lechem hapanim
b'Shabbat, and you only inaugurate the שולחן shulchan with the bread on
שבת. Shabbat. ולא את המנורה אלא בשבעה נרות בין הערביים, V'lo et
hamenorah ela b'shivah nerot bein ha-arbayim, and only you only inaugurate the
מנורה menorah with lighting the seven candles in the afternoon. So you
have to do the classic עבודה avodah on the thing to inaugurate
it. So this does not seem exactly relevant except the point about
the outer מזבח mizbeach and the תמיד של שחר tamid shel shachar
seem to sort of be somewhat of רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's argument
that since the תמיד של שחר tamid shel shachar is the sort
of foundation, you don't want to make a choice to skip the
תמיד של שחר tamid shel shachar and just do the תמיד של
בין הערביים, tamid shel bein ha-arbayim, and that could be why he
has his problem with doing just the תמיד של בין הערביים. tamid
shel bein ha-arbayim. Okay, so we will see about all of this
in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the first issue
of the גמרא Gemara though which is not the debate of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. בעי רב חייא
בר אבין מרב חסדא, Ba-ei Rav Chiya bar Avin me-Rav Chisda, רב
חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar Avin asked the following question from
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. ציבור שאין להם תמידים ומוספין איזה מהם קודם.
Tzibur she-ein lahem tmidim u-musafim eizeh me-hem kodem. So this is a
great question I think, similar to questions we had before in the
גמרא, Gemara, when you have to make difficult choices, right? You can't
do everything. You only have a certain amount of קרבנות. korbanot. You
have תמידים, tmidim, you have מוספין, musafim, which one are you going
to do? And it's actually a very easy case if you think
about שבת. Shabbat. שבת Shabbat and you only have two lambs. So
two lambs is what you need for your two תמידים, tmidim, two
lambs is what you need for your מוסף, musaf, which ones are
you going to bring? Okay, what's the issue? קודם Kodem here does
not mean come first, it means which one are you going to
give preference to? Which one are you going to bring? Okay, obviously
you first bring a תמיד tamid and then a מוסף, musaf, but
that's not the question. Okay היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case?
אילימא תמידים דיומא ומוספים דיומא, Ilima tmidim d'yoma u-musafim d'yoma,
so you have to choose between the תמיד tamid of שבת Shabbat
and the מוסף musaf of שבת. Shabbat. פשיטא תמידים עדיפי. Pshita tmidim
adifei.
Of course you're going to bring the תמיד tamid first. Why? דהוי
ליה תדיר. D'havei lei tadir. First of all we actually have a
whole, thank you so much, we actually have a whole a whole
what do you call it? A whole hierarchy in a פרק perek
in זבחים Zevachim about which comes first, right? About, you know, the
whole תדיר ושאינו תדיר תדיר קודם, tadir v'she-eino tadir tadir kodem, you
know כל המקודש מחברו קודם לחברו. kol hamikudash me-chaveiro kodem l'chaveiro. Of
course the problem happens what happens when those lists don't match up?
You have one thing that's תדיר tadir and the other thing is
more מקודש. mikudash. But here the גמרא Gemara says by שבת Shabbat
it's easy. Why? Because first of all the מוסף musaf is no
more קדוש kadosh than the תמיד. tamid. And the תמיד tamid is
more תדיר. tadir. So of course the תמיד tamid gets preference. Okay,
notice it says תדיר ומקודש. tadir u-mikudash. Now what does it mean
מקודש? mikudash? So רש''י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say it doesn't
mean it's holier than the מוסף, musaf, but it's at least as
holy as the מוסף. musaf. It's the תמיד tamid of שבת. Shabbat.
So the תמיד tamid of שבת Shabbat is at least as מקודש
mikudash as מוסף musaf of שבת. Shabbat. So clearly you're going to
give preference to the תמיד. tamid. אלא, Ela, here's the interesting question.
תמידים דלמחר ומוספים דהאידנא. Tmidim d'limachar u-musafim d'ha-idna. You have four lambs
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and you know for whatever reason
or you're not expecting to get any more lambs before tomorrow. Even
if you get lambs, they have to be checked four days in
advance. So even if somebody showed up at your doorstep with lambs,
you couldn't use them tomorrow. Okay, so you have to choose. What
am I going to do with these two lambs? Do I seize
the day and say bring today's מוסף musaf and whatever happens tomorrow
happens tomorrow, it's not my concern? Or do you say let's plan
ahead and we'll say we'll save two of the lambs for tomorrow
so at least we'll have the תמידים tmidim tomorrow. Okay, and that
could be, so when the, so one of the questions is should
you address today's concerns you know and ignore tomorrow's concerns? The other
way of also asking it is even if I'm considering tomorrow's concerns,
which concerns are more weighty? Is it more weighty to have a
תמיד, tamid, you know, of non-שבת Shabbat versus a מוסף musaf of
שבת? Shabbat? Okay, so let's take a look at how the גמרא
Gemara frames it. That also תדיר tadir
doesn't the, the comes first doesn't mean that it replaces?
Right, that is a good point and I believe I'd have to
check again the גמרא Gemara in זבחים. Zevachim. Right, the idea of
קודם kodem which is if you have all of them and the
question is sequencing them as opposed to which one are you going
to give more preference to and allow, you know, and allow the
other to fall by the wayside and just do one. I think
the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim and the משניות Mishnayot there sort
of had both cases but you're right, the emphasis was certainly on,
I think the משנה Mishnah had the question of sort of order
and the גמרא Gemara translated as I'm remembering correctly into actually preferring
one over the other if you had to choose between them. But
you're right, certainly the גמרא Gemara here is doing that, that assumes
קודם kodem translates into choosing one of them over the other. That's
absolutely correct. Okay, so what do I have to do if I
have to choose between today and tomorrow?
תמידים דלמחר מוספים דהאידנא. Tmidim d'limachar musafim d'ha-idna. Do we say תמידים
עדיפי שכן תדיר, tmidim adifei she-ken tadir, you give greater weight to
the תמידים tmidim because they are more תדיר? tadir? Regular, they're every
day. Don't have a better example of תדיר tadir than the תמידים.
temidim. או דילמא מוספים עדיף דהוו למקודש o dilma musafim adif dehavu
limekudash
or maybe the מוספים musafim are more important because they are holier.
Why are they holier? Because at least there's a מוסף musaf of
שבת Shabbos as opposed to a תמיד tamid of tomorrow. Okay. So
which one are you going to bring, give greater, give greater preference
to? Why is that considered מקודש? mekudash?
ורש"י ve-Rashi has two לשונות. lishonos. One is what I've been implicitly
saying, because today is שבת Shabbos and tomorrow is חול. chol. So
a קרבן korban of a קדוש kadosh day is considered to be
related to the identity of the day and have implicitly greater קדושה,
kedusha,
you know, or play a role that's greater in terms of connecting
to something of קדוש kadosh than a קרבן korban of a regular
day. That's at least the assumption. The other explanation of רש"י Rashi
is
that מקודש mekudash doesn't really mean מקודש. mekudash. מקודש mekudash just means
like it's like it's today's issue as opposed to tomorrow's issue, which
is a fruity way of saying it as מקודש, mekudash, but I
think it in a way it gives it even a little bit
more interest. It's like, do I plan for tomorrow or do I
say tomorrow's not my issue, I have to do the best I
can today? So that's in a, I think that's like also like
a fascinating type of a question, you know, about how do you
go about those things. So that's the other way רש"י Rashi says
מקודש. mekudash. It's not like a שבת Shabbos קרבן korban is holier
than a חול chol קרבן, korban, but it's like, okay, this is
like the קדושה kedusha is presenting itself to us right now and
therefore we should address it now and not worry about tomorrow. So
it's a hard read into the word מקודש, mekudash, but I think
it frames the question in an interesting way. It's also unique, fairly,
I guess a unique case because as you said, you can't rely
on providence to come up with something for you in the meantime.
Right. It would be an easier if I said that tomorrow, may
who knows what'll happen, tomorrow maybe it'll work out. And of course
you could say, well, just focus on today. But we're assuming that,
you know, you need four days to check the קרבנות. korbanot. We'll
talk about that tomorrow. I mean, what if somebody showed up at
my doorstep and said I've been checking it for the last four
days, can I trust him, do we have to check it? But
right, I think that the גמרא Gemara is framing it as we
can be certain that we're not going to have tomorrow. But still.
And the checking is really לכתחילה lechatchila not בדיעבד. bedieved. It's no,
it seems to really be בדיעבד bedieved and we're going to see
about that. Okay, but we'll see. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so what am I going to do? אמר ליה תניתוה, amar
lei tanituha, we taught in a משנה, Mishna, התמידים אין מעכבין את
המוספים ולא המוספים מעכבין את התמידים, hatmidim ein meakvin et hamusafim velo
hamusafim meakvin et hatmidim, ולא המוספים מעכבין זה את זה, velo hamusafim
meakvin ze et ze, and the מוספים musafim don't hold each other
back. Now, what does that prove anything? היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's
the case that it says the תמידים temidim don't hold back the
מוספים musafim and the מוסף musaf doesn't hold back the תמידים? temidim?
אילימא דאית ליה, ileima de-is lei,
that you have all of the קרבנות korbanot in front of you,
we have all the animals, and when it says it doesn't hold
it back, it means ולקדם, ulekadem,
that if you did it out of order, it's not a problem.
Meaning not hold back like if you don't have it, it's not
a problem. If you reversed the order, it's not a problem. You
did the מוסף musaf before the תמיד. tamid. והתניא, vehatanya, but we
know that is a problem. מנין שלא יהא דבר קודם לתמיד של
שחר, minayin shelo yehe davar kodem letamid shel shachar, how do I
know something can't precede the תמיד? tamid? תלמוד לומר וערך עליה העולה,
talmud lomar ve-arach aleha ha-olah, you should put on it, which literally
means the fire, the עולה. olah. But we learn on it, it
means that everything goes after the עולה. olah. ואמר רבא העולה עולה
ראשונה, ve-amar Rava ha-olah olah rishona, the עולה olah means the תמיד,
tamid, the first עולה, olah, the first thing on the fire, and
nothing goes before it. So therefore it can't mean that if you
do it out of order, it's not a problem. Now the גמרא's
Gemara going to say, no, that's only לכתחילה. lechatchila. It could mean
if you do it out of order, it's not a problem, it
just means בדיעבד bedieved it's not a problem. But okay, we're saying
the משנה Mishna does not mean you have them and you did
the wrong order, which anyway is probably not פשט peshat of the
משנה. Mishna. אלא פשיטא דלית ליה, ela peshita deleis lei, the משנה
Mishna means you don't have all of them and you're choosing to
do one or the other, the תמיד tamid or the מוסף, musaf,
and one is being done and the other is not. ואי ביומיה
אמאי, ve-i beyomei amai,
so if it is that you are choosing today between תמיד tamid
and מוסף, musaf, why is it saying that the מוסף musaf doesn't
hold back, the תמיד tamid doesn't hold back the מוסף, musaf, which
means sounds like it means you can do the מוסף? musaf? תדיר
ומקודש תדיר עדיף, tadir umekudash tadir adif, you should be doing the
תמיד, tamid, you shouldn't be doing the מוסף. musaf. Why are you
choosing to do the מוסף musaf today and not the תדיר? tadir?
Now, again, that's not a great question because the משנה's Mishna not
talking about לכתחילה lechatchila what you're choosing. The משנה Mishna is talking
about whether it in the end of the day it was a
problem, whether you were still יוצא. yotzei. So it could have been
you should have chosen to do the תמיד tamid first. For whatever
reason, you chose to do the מוסף musaf first, right? And it's
still saying you're still יוצא yotzei even though you did the מוסף
musaf without the תמיד. tamid. Okay, but the גמרא's Gemara understanding, maybe
because later in the משנה Mishna רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is also
discussing what type of choices you should or should not make, שוגג,
shogeg, מזיד meizid and so on, it's also understanding that you're making
a לכתחילה lechatchila choice. So what type of a לכתחילה lechatchila choice
can you have made to have done the מוסף musaf without doing
the תמיד? tamid? That wouldn't have been possible if it was the
same day. אלא לאו דלמחר, ela lav delemachar, that it must be
the case that you are choosing for tomorrow. Now, how are you
choosing for tomorrow to do a מוסף musaf without a תמיד? tamid?
What does it mean? So here's the case. ותני אין מעכבין זה
את זה vesani ein meakvin ze et ze and we said it
doesn't hold back. אמעכבי אהדדי נינהו. ameakvei ahadadi ninu. So how can
you be choosing to do a מוסף musaf without doing a תמיד?
tamid? It's not means tomorrow's מוסף. musaf. It means you're choosing today's
מוסף musaf and foregoing tomorrow's תמיד. tamid. So here's again how the
גמרא Gemara reads the case. גמרא Gemara reads the משנה Mishna like
I would say is פשט peshat that there's only that you're you're
doing only one set of קרבנות korbanot and not the others. But
it goes further to say that we're not just talking about בדיעבד,
be-di-avad, we're talking about you're making a choice. So therefore it's saying,
look, if you choose to do the תמידין temidin and not the
מוסף, musaf, that's okay. If you chose to do the מוסף musaf
and not the תמיד, tamid, that's okay. Now it can't be saying
that on the same day, cause on the same day it wouldn't
be okay. You should be choosing the תמיד. tamid. So what it's
saying is that you're choosing between today and tomorrow. Today's מוסף musaf
or tomorrow's תמיד. tamid. So if you chose to do today's מוסף
musaf and forgo tomorrow's תמיד, tamid, that's fine. You chose to do
tomorrow's תמיד tamid and to forgo today's מוסף, musaf, that's also fine.
So it's an equivalent choice. Okay, there's no specific preference. So that's
what it comes to choosing to read the משנה mishna as not
a בדיעבד be-di-avad question, but as a לכתחילה le-chatchila question. Okay, so
that's the attempt at learning it from the משנה. mishna. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, so Abaye back, lo, no, that's not פשט pshat in
the משנה. mishna. לעולם דאית
להו, Le-olam de-is lehu, the משנה's mishna talking that you have all
the קרבנות korbanot in front of us ולקדם, u-lekadem, and the point
of the משנה mishna is if you did them out of order,
it's still okay. ודקא קשיא לך, Ve-de-ka-kasha lecha, you were bothered, oh
we know that the עולה olah has to come first, the תמיד
tamid has to come first, שלא יהא דבר קודם קודם, she-lo yihe
davar kodem kodem, nothing can come before the תמיד. tamid. מצוה בעלמא
הוא, Mitzvah be-alma hu, that's just a מצוה mitzvah to לכתחילה, le-chatchila,
בדיעבד be-di-avad it's okay. So Abaye says the משנה mishna is not
talking about לכתחילה le-chatchila and choosing, it's talking about בדיעבד be-di-avad and
you did the wrong order. You could have also said it's talking
about בדיעבד be-di-avad and you chose one over the other, but it's
still not telling you לכתחילה le-chatchila what choice you should make. So
you really can't prove it from the משנה. mishna. The משנה's mishna
not telling you what's the right choice. The משנה's mishna telling you
what happens if you went ahead and did it. Okay, so now
we are going to continue to see if we can answer this
question. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear: אין פוחתין מששה טלאים המבוקרים
בלשכת הטלאים כדי לשבת ולשני ימים טובים של ראש השנה. Ein pochsin
mi-shisha t'layim ha-mevukarim de-lishkat ha-t'layim kedei le-shabbat u-lishnei yamim tovim shel rosh
hashana. Okay,
there's no fewer, there was this לשכה lishka that they had in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I have to start now bringing my
diagram as well, but they had anyway an office, a room, where
they kept sheep and they kept them, you know, a
little what they call like a what's it called when you have
some backup there? Anyway, a
reserve, thank you, a little bit of a reserve, and they had
six sheep as he is not such a reserve, you know, you
had six sheep that were checked in advance, four days in advance,
because they have to be checked four days in advance. Why? Because
it sounds like we're going to change it in a minute, but
it sounds like cause what will happen? You want to do a
worst-case scenario. Now of course you have time to plan for worst-case
scenario, you know what the קרבנות korbanot are going to be, but
okay, the worst-case scenario is שבת, Shabbat, two days of ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, the only two day יום טוב yom tov they have
in Israel. Okay, and those types of cases presumably you're not having
a chance to go out and run and find sheep and check
them and so on. You have to draw on your reserves. So
you're going to want, you know, you need the two for שבת
Shabbat and then you need the two for the תמידין temidin of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and you're going to want them all there.
Okay, and therefore and that's what you have in that room. Now
the point is that it's all very nice, that satisfied your תמיד
tamid needs for שבת Shabbat and ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, but you're
not satisfying your מוסף musaf needs for שבת Shabbat and ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashana. So you see that when we're planning our reserves, our
primary concern even in advance is for the תמידין temidin and not
for the full complement of the first day. You know, if we're
not focusing on what do I fully need for שבת, Shabbat, what
do I fully need for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana by the way is like seven lambs, right? So if ראש
השנה Rosh Hashana came first, it was ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and
then שבת, Shabbat, why don't you make sure that you have ten
lambs there? So if ראש השנה Rosh Hashana hits you first, you
got it all there for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. Okay, so let's
you can imagine that the maybe the תמידין temidin were the responsibility
of somebody
and you know, their job was to make sure that the daily
oh, that's an interesting point. Maybe it was just procedures, but for
יום טוב, yom tov, you're not going to rely on that guy.
Right. Well, in a way that's also what the גמרא gemara is
going to say, that this was not really saying that we you
know, this okay, well we'll see how the גמרא's gemara answer, but
let's take a look. So the גמרא gemara says,
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דאית ליה תמידין ומוספין,
Ilei-ma de-is lei temidin u-musafin, if the idea is that you're having
enough lambs for all your תמידין ומוספין, temidin u-musafin, then the גמרא
gemara says I gotta tell you, it's more than six. טובא הוי,
Tuva ha-vei, that's more than six. It's a lot more for all
your תמידין ומוספין temidin u-musafin on שבת Shabbat and ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashana. I mean שבת Shabbat is not so more, שבת Shabbat is
just two lambs. The מוספין musafin of the other days are like,
you know, seven lambs and two cows and and a ram.
אלא לאו ella lav by the way, you know, it's just worth
just very bracketly pointing this out, we almost always ignore the specific
content of what the מוספין musafin are, but you know, to appreciate
the fact that all מוספין, musafin, you know, are often like huge
קרבנות, korbanot, seven sheep, this, that. שבת Shabbat is like this very
almost modest, that's exactly what I was looking for, modest קרבנות korbanot
of just two of just two, and it's actually exactly paralleling the
תמידין, temidin, which in a way, you know, sort of like the
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the נשמה יתירה, neshama yeteira, it's like a
simple sense, it's a doubling but in a very quiet way as
opposed to the more expansive nature of יום טוב yom tov and
the מוספין musafin there which are much greater. Okay, but anyway so
the גמרא's gemara saying if it was for the real full number
then it would be a lot of animals. אלא לאו Ella lav
It must be that you have, ושמע מינה ד-, Ve-shamma mina de-,
I'm sorry, אלא לאו דלית ליה, Ela lav de-lais lei, sorry, you
don't have enough animals for all, and you're having to choose which
are the ones you most want to focus your reserves on, and
you're going to focus your reserves on the תמיד, tamid, and you're
not going to care about the מוסף. musaf. אלא לאו דלית ליה
ושמע מינה תמידין עדיפי, Ela lav de-lais lei ve-shamma mina temidin adifei,
that you'd rather make sure that you have all the תמידים, temidim,
even if you're not going to have all of the מוספים. musafim.
So that sounds like a pretty good proof that that's our primary
concern, even tomorrow's תמיד tamid over today's...
Okay. And רש"י, Rashi, by the way, makes it even sharper, that
it's not just a planning issue, it's also an execution issue. Let's
say שבת Shabbos comes first. Okay, so I have four, I have
now six animals here. Okay, six sheep. The implication is, what am
I going to bring on שבת? Shabbos? How many am I going
to bring? I have six sheep, and I now need two for
תמיד tamid and two for מוסף. musaf. But presumably based on the
way it's framed it, you have enough for שבת Shabbos and ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. You have שבת Shabbos and then two days ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. What am I going to bring today on שבת?
Shabbos? Presumably just two, in order that I can leave the rest
over for ראש השנה's Rosh Hashanah תמיד. tamid. So I am specifically
choosing
tomorrow's תמיד, tamid, right, over today's מוסף. musaf. No? Does that happen?
There's שבת Shabbos and then ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? Well, when they
were מקדש על פי הראיה mekadesh al pi ha-re'iyah certainly, but nowadays
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is לא אד"ו ראש, lo adu rosh, so
that wouldn't happen actually, right, with our calendar that wouldn't happen. But
in this context logically it could. So the גמרא's Gemara saying, so
you see what you're doing is you're choosing tomorrow's תמיד tamid over
today's מוסף. musaf. Okay, so that takes precedence. Okay, so that should
be a pretty good proof. So
גמרא Gemara says, לא, Lo, לעולם דאית ליה, le-olam de-is lei, really
we would assume you have enough קרבנות korbanos for everything, this is
not talking about what you minimally have to ensure. Okay, so then
why does it say six? והכי קאמר, Ve-hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means: אין פוחתין משישה טלאים המבוקרים בלשכת הטלאים ארבעה ימים קודם
שחיטה, Ein pochtin me-shishah telayim ha-mevukarin be-lishkas ha-telayim arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah,
that you have no fewer than six sheep in there with, you
know, that are you prepare four days before. Meaning what it's basically
saying is is that this has nothing to do with שבת Shabbos
and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. We're going to say it in a
minute. שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was just a, like,
a
mnemonic to remember the number of six, but that really isn't the
point. And the point is really that you always are going to
have a backup. But it really has nothing to do with שבת
Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The way רש"י Rashi is going
to explain it, just to clarify it, and שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzes
explains it a little clearer, it's like this: is that you start,
you introduce every day two new
animals into this. It's like a rotation. Okay, so if you have
six that have been checked the last three days. So today, you
need to draw on two for your תמיד, tamid, and you put
two more in, and they start checking the two new that you've
put in. By the time those two have had their four days,
you'll have gone through the reserve and you'll be up to those
two and you'll replace it. You sort of see how that happens?
Like if you imagine this like queue, you know, two, two, two,
you take... so they've been checked, this would have been checked Sunday,
this would have been checked Monday, this would have been checked Tuesday.
Now it's Wednesday. So the Sunday... actually that wouldn't work. The ones
that are actually... because really you should really need eight. But the
point is is that the Sunday, Monday, Tuesday,
Wednesday... the ones that you need stuff for that actually was checked
on שבת. Shabbos. שבת, Shabbos, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday. Okay, so it was
checked. So it's Thursday. Right, that's the funny thing is that you
have six and it's Thursday. All right, the שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzes
works this out. I'm not exactly... but anyway, so it's Thursday. You
draw on the one that was checked on Sunday, you put in
two new ones today on Thursday. What happened on Wednesday? I don't
know. It really logically should be eight, not six. The שיטה מקובצת
Shittah Mekubetzes works it out. But the point is is that this
is a reserve just in order to give you the four days
of checking and keep things rotating, and it really has nothing to
do with choosing between שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. It's
just the way you said: this is the job of making sure
there's always a ready תמיד tamid to go. And it's not at
all about choosing between the תמידים temidim and the מוספים. musafim. How
do you make sure there's a ready תמיד tamid to go? You
have a backup of things that have been checked. There's always two
for a תמיד, tamid, then you have a standing order and then
you constantly are replenishing it and giving enough time for the four
days to check it, and that's what it's talking about.
Okay. אין פוחתין משישה טלאים המבוקרים בלשכת הטלאים ארבעה ימים קודם שחיטה.
Ein pochtin me-shishah telayim ha-mevukarin be-lishkas ha-telayim arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah. They
have a four day... it's they've been checked for the last four
days. ומאן היא? U-man hi? Who is it? בן בג בג. Ben
Bag Bag. He has been בן בג בג. Ben Bag Bag. דתניא,
De-tanya, בן בג בג Ben Bag Bag אומר, omer, מניין לתמיד שטעון
ביקור ארבעה ימים minayin le-tamid she-ta'un bikkur arba'ah yamim קודם שחיטה? kodem
shechitah? So בן בג בג Ben Bag Bag explicitly says it requires
four days of
checking. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, תשמרו להקריב לי במועדו, Tishmeru le-hakriv li
be-mo'ado, you should observe to do the תמיד tamid in its right
time. ולהלן הוא אומר, U-le-halan hu omer, and later it says והיה
לכם למשמרת עד ארבעה עשר יום, Ve-hayah lachem le-mishmeres ad arba'ah asar
yom, by the פסח, Pesach, and that was given on the tenth.
מה להלן טעון ביקור ארבעה ימים קודם שחיטה אף כאן טעון ביקור
ארבעה ימים קודם שחיטה. Mah le-halan ta'un bikkur arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah
af kan ta'un bikkur arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah. And not only that,
what's more relevant... And not only that, what's more relevant is that
he says it is what requires ביקור ארבעה ימים? bikur arba yamim?
לתמיד. LeTamid. Not every קרבן, Korban, just the תמיד. Tamid. So why
do we have this as having enough for—why are we focused on
תמידים? temidim? So it's not just like Dove said, "Well, this is
the job of the guy who is supplying the תמידים, temidim, somebody
else does the מוספים." musafim. The need to have a backup and
to have invested four days so that they're ready is only for
the תמיד. tamid. Only the תמיד tamid requires the four-day checking. Other
things do not require the four-day checking, and therefore you have a
specific backup here for the תמידים, temidim, things that have been checked
a few days ago that they're ready to supply with the new
תמיד. tamid. That's what's going on here. There is nothing to do
between choosing between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and ויום ve'Yom and שבת.
Shabbos. I mean, between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and שבת Shabbos and
one day's תמיד tamid from the other day's תמיד. tamid. It's a
totally different thing that is going on here. Okay, it actually, by
the way, I think is a nice point, the combination of—I mean,
I have to think about it more, but just at the outset,
the combination of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, which is once a
year, and the תמיד, tamid, and it's basically saying because the most
likely thing—it's sort of like the message of the beginning of צו,
Tzav, where רש״י Rashi says it's like why does it say צו
את בני ישראל? Tzav es Bnei Yisrael? You know, it says because
זירוז מיד כאן ולדורות, zeeruz miyad kan uledoros, you know, you need
the דוקא davka to encourage the כהנים Kohanim to do this thing
of
removing the ashes. So why do you need to encourage them? So
one you could say is because it's a dirty job, it's like
taking out the garbage, so you can speak about the importance of
doing even the cleanup and how that's also serving and so on.
But the other point is because it's every single day, and every
single day you can start being negligent about things. So I think
there's something very nice about the idea that the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is a big deal, once in a year,
four days preparation, and the תמיד, tamid, which is every single
day, which you could easily start to ignore and just take for
granted and do without bothering every single day, that requires the same
degree of preparation as the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Nothing else in
between. But at least those two extremes, and I think there's an
important point to be said about that. Okay, so anyway, that's what
he says and that's what's going on here. So אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, הני שיתא שבעה הוי. hani shita shiva havi. One
minute, there's a problem that those six really translate into seven. How
is that? Because he still assumes, although we said that this is
for the תמיד, tamid, he is still working—I've already sort of jumped
ahead where the גמרא Gemara says that for שבת Shabbos and ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah is just a mnemonic. He still assumes that we're
specifically talking to anticipate the תמידים temidim for שבת Shabbos and ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. But the reason we're focusing only on the תמידים
temidim is only the תמידים temidim needed a backup, only the תמידים
temidim needed four days' checking in advance. But that's still the issue
is to be concerned about שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
So he says one minute, I'm not sure how six is going
to be enough. You're going to need seven. Why? שבת Shabbos and
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is going to roll around, you'll have used
up your whole backup supply, and now it's going to be
the morning after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, and you won't have had
a chance to start getting new sheep yet. And so how are
you going to be able to bring the next morning? So why
is it? He says, האי איכא צפרא, hai ika tzafra, there's the
next
morning, דתילתא בשבתא, d'tilsa b'Shabsa, on the third of שבת. Shabbos. That's
assuming that it was first שבת Shabbos and then ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. Others have different גרסאות girsaos assuming it was first ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and then שבת. Shabbos. So how is six going to
be enough? What about the next morning if you're going to need
all those days to check? So it says ולטעמיך, u'letaameich, and according
to you, תמניא הוו, tamnya havu, there are eight days, דאיכא דפניא
דמעלי שבתא. d'ika d'panya d'ma'alei Shabsa. How about ערב שבת? erev Shabbos?
Presumably you're not going to have time to check on ערב שבת
erev Shabbos to make sure that, you know, what does רש״י Rashi
say? דקודם שיקריבו תמיד של בין הערבים. dekodem sheyakrivu tamid shel bein
haarbayim. Yeah, because the afternoon one on Friday. On Friday. That you're
not going to have time presumably to replace it. It's almost about
to be שבת Shabbos and you're going to have to use that
and you won't have time to replace it. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's not a problem.
דבתר דאיקריב קאמר. dbasar de-ikriv ka'amar. So what it means that you
have six is six after you've brought the day's complement. So you're
going into שבת ראש השנה Shabbos Rosh Hashanah you're going to have
six. But מכל מקום, mikol makom, שבעה הוו, shiva havu, what do
you do about
the next morning? Now again, what's interesting also is you could say
that if you need four days of checking, you've really got a
problem
because how do you get something that's been checked for four days
starting in the starting that morning? Why is it just a problem
the next morning? Why is it a problem for the next four
days? How are you going to replenish your
supply? So it actually sounds here a little bit
that you don't have to be the one that necessarily checks it.
As long as you can go ahead and buy one from somebody
who says that they've been checking it, you the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash can buy from a supplier that's been checking it. That might
be okay. But the point is still by the next morning you
won't have a chance to have gotten replenished your stock yet. So
how is that going to be okay? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא תנא בעלמא קאי. ela tanna b'alma ka'ei. You're right, we're not
really talking about שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. When we
say six, we don't really mean שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. We just mean you should have a backup. ומה כדי לשבת
ובשני ימים טובים של ראש השנה? u'ma kedei l'Shabbos u'veshnei yamim tovim
shel Rosh Hashanah? Why do we say enough for שבת Shabbos and
ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? סימנא בעלמא. simna b'alma.
It's just a way of remembering, it's a mnemonic, but you're really
right. If you were about to go into a שבת Shabbos ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you'd have more in your backup supply. You'd increase
your reserves. We're not really talking about שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. We're just saying as a general rule, you should have
six sheep in the on the ready. Wait, what exactly is the
problem with obtaining the sheep on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Is it because of אין שבות במקדש? Ein shevus b'mikdash? That's
interesting. I mean, would אין שבות במקדש Ein shevus b'mikdash include the
types of commerce and purchasing in order to specifically also to plan
for after שבת Shabbos and יום טוב? Yom Tov? אין שבות במקדש
Ein shevus b'mikdash usually has to do with the act of הקרבה,
hakravah, right as
well, right in the moment. Right now I'm being מקריב makriv and
I'm a כהן kohen and I've got something bleeding and I can
put on a bandage or something that's allowing me to do the
הקרבה hakravah now. I mean, I would say two things. It's an
interesting question, but I would try to say two things. One is
that commerce, I think, would be of a different
quality, sort of like doing business in the מקדש Mikdash on שבת
Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. And the other is that I'm
not sure that I would say that to plan for afterwards, usually
that's to enable the הקרבה hakravah that's going on today. You say
this was the system, this is part of what we do today.
Every day we just get new ones. Right, that's a good point.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
so if you take a look by the way of תוספות, Tosafos,
we're about this idea that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the
הוה אמינא havamino does not have to be the one doing the
checking. This little תוספות Tosafos מכל מקום זיין הוי, Mikol makom zayin
havei, תוספות Tosafos says on נ עמוד א Nun amud aleph דבשלמא
בין הערבים דרישא, Debishlama bein ha'arbayim derisha, אף על פי שצריך ביקור
ארבעה ימים. Af al pi shetzarich bikur arba'ah yamim.
I understand that the afternoon תמיד tamid of
after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, that you can get. How can you
get a קרבן korban in time? It's right after ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. How did you check it for four days? So תוספות Tosafos
says, יטרח וימצא מבוקרים. Yitrach veyimtza mivukarim.
You could go ahead, you could start asking around and find somebody
who has checked sheep to supply the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. שהמבקרים
היו מבקרים אותם כדי למכרן, Shehamivakrim hayu mivakrim osam k'dei limchran,
that people were in the business. They would, they would supply the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with sheep and they would prepare it four
days in advance. Maybe they'd come with their certificate of having checked
it or whatever it was, but they would be suppliers. The problem
is אבל בצפרא לא יכול בלילה לטרוח ולבקש מבקרים. Aval batzafra lo
yachol balaila litroach u'levakesh mivukarim. You can't get in you can't get
ahold of the suppliers at night and you have to bring one
first thing in the morning. So the interesting thing of this תוספות
Tosafos is that I don't think we would've expected that. If there's
an idea that you have to check four days in advance, we
would've thought that I mean you're not allowed to outsource it. Like
that's the בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash responsibility to check in advance. And
here we're finding that no, somebody else could have done the checking
and just supply it to you. So that's what we're now saying.
We're saying like this. Why do we say just to remind us
what we said, why do we say that this thing has six
sheep? We thought it meant that you were going to ensure you
had the תמידים temidim for שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and you didn't care so much about the מוספים. musafim. So it
says, so you're choosing תמידים temidim over מוספים? musafim? It says, no,
no. The reason that we are focusing more on תמידים temidim is
it requires more attention and preparation because you need to have מבוקרים
mivukarim like בן בג בג. Ben Bag Bag. You have to check
them in advance for תמידים, temidim, which is not true for the
מוספים. musafim. That you don't have to check them. So that's why
we have a backup of תמידים. temidim. So then it's saying okay
and therefore enough to supply שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
So then it asks okay, but if you go into a שבת
Shabbos ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, six isn't going to be enough. You're
going to need one first thing the next morning. How are you
going to get one first thing the next morning? And as we
see, maybe you could get suppliers for afterwards, but first thing the
next morning how are you going to get it? So the גמרא
Gemara says, it doesn't literally mean שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was a way to
know, remember the idea of six. Okay, but the basic point is
that you have six backed up. If you're going into שבת Shabbos
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you'll get a few more in reserve. אי
הכי נמי. Ei hachi nami. And how do we know this? One
minute. So the גמרא Gemara says דיקא נמי, Deika nami, that's also
can be inferred from the language דקתני כדי לשבת, Dekatani k'dei l'Shabbos,
enough for שבת, Shabbos, ולא קתני לשבת, V'lo katani l'Shabbos, for the
sake of שבת. Shabbos. So כדי k'dei somehow means like equal to
the amount of שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah but it's
not a literally saying that that's
the purpose. ולב' ימים טובים של ראש השנה, U'l'v' yamim tovim shel
Rosh Hashanah, שמע מינה, Shema mina, that's a good point. So what
then is the idea of six if it's not to supply for
a שבת Shabbos and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah emergency? So here again
the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet tries to explain. Let me see if
I can do a better job than I did last time. If
you take a look at the ח Ches here in the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet for those who want to follow this, it's in
the tiny print so if you get out your huge magnifying glass
in the left-hand column, he tries to explain the significance of six.
I'll read it to you. He says like this: כיצד מהרה יבנה
בית המקדש אם ראוי המזבח להתחנך ברביעי בשבת. Keitzad mehera yibaneh Beis
Hamikdash im ra'uy hamizbe'ach lehitchanech birevi'i b'Shabbos. Let's say we're starting to
bring קרבנות korbanos on a Wednesday. So how do you get ready
to start bringing קרבנות korbanos on a Wednesday? צריך שיחזיר לבקר תמידים
של יום החינוך מיום השבת שלפניו. Tzarich sheyachzir l'vaker temidim shel yom
hachinuch miyom haShabbos shelefaneha. So you start getting ready on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay, you get two sheep ready on שבת. Shabbos. You're going to
check those two sheep to people. So I am, it's the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet the ח, Ches, it's like near the bottom of
the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, so you start getting those two sheep ready
on שבת Shabbos so you're going to have שבת, Shabbos, Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday to check it and therefore you'll be able to use them
come Wednesday. של יום החינוך מיום השבת שלפניו דהיינו ארבעה ימים לשתי
הקרבות הללו לבד מיום שחיטה. Shel yom hachinuch miyom haShabbos shelefaneha dehaynu
arba'ah yamim l'shtei hakravos halalu levad mi'yom shechitah. You can't count the
day itself. It has to be four days
before. וביום אחד. U'v'yom echad. and then on Sunday יקח שנים אחרים
לצורך יום ה׳. yikach shnayim acherim letzorech yom hei. You get two
more and those will serve you for
Thursday. ובשני בשבת Ubesheni bashabbos on Monday, שנים אחרים לצורך יום ו׳
shnayim acherim letzorech yom vav then you have two more and those
will serve you on Friday. So now you have six that are
checked. Okay, but now there's a day gap. Here's the problem. You
have six that are checked. You took two on שבת, Shabbos, two
on Sunday, two on Monday. Today is Tuesday, right? So what are
you going to do? So let's take a
look. וביום שבת? נמצא בלשכת הטלאים... Ubeyom Shabbos? Nimtza belishkas hatlaim... ובשלישי
בשבת שנים אחרים. Ubishlishi bashabbos shnayim acherim. Okay, so 'cause then it's
going to be able, right? 'Cause if you want to
rotate,
ובשלישי בשבת שנים אחרים ליום השבת Ubishlishi bashabbos shnayim acherim leyom Hashabbos
to serve next שבת. Shabbos. נמצא בלשכת הטלאים ח׳ טלאים קודם שיתחיל
לחנך המזבח ברביעי. Nimtza belishkas hatlaim ches tlaim kodem sheyatchil lechanach hamizbeach
berevii. So you start with eight which are before you actually get
started with the הקרבה hakrava which you're going to do on Wednesday.
Now, that system works, right? If you come into Wednesday, you
have eight, you take two, you resupply two more. Okay. So now
and now what happens on Thursday? On Thursday you're able to draw
on, right? If you've had here שבת, Shabbos, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday backup,
right? And you come on Wednesday, so you take from the bottom
of the pile, the שבת Shabbos which had a four day, right?
And now you have to resupply at the top and you keep
on drawing one from the bottom and resupplying at the top. That
worked, but that's eight, eight sheep in the לשכה, lishka, not six.
So how is he going to deal with it? So let's take
a look. He says,
where were we? ח׳ טלאים קודם שיתחיל לחנך. Ches tlaim kodem sheyatchil
lechanach. וברביעי בשבת שיהיה יום החינוך כשיקח שנים המבוקרים ארבעה ימים Uberevii
bashabbos sheyiheye yom hachinuch kesheyikach shnayim hamivukarim arba yamim when you take
the two that have been checked four days, the two that were
put in on שבת, Shabbos,
עדיין נשארו בלשכה ו׳ טלאים. Adayin nisharu belishka vav tlaim. So then
for a while there will only be six there. You took your
two out from the bottom of the queue. Okay. And now it
had eight, now it only has six. So there's six before you
resupply the queue, which you're going to do later that day. So
it's a little weak answer. Okay? You understand? Really you need eight.
You need eight to keep the keep it rotating. But when it
says you need six, it means even in that interim, when you've
taken the two for today and are yet to replenish it, you're
going to have six. Okay, so it's funny. You or I would
have said you need eight, but that's how he's explaining why it
says six. Says, is there a problem with checking on שבת? Shabbos?
No, that has to do with the points that תוספות Tosafos are
saying that yes, it's sort of what we have to do in
order to ensure the regular working of the מקדש. Mikdash. You know,
to the degree preparing after שבת Shabbos without doing a מלאכה melacha
is mostly דרבנן derabbanan anyway. So yeah, I mean, so that actually
was okay. I mean the issue about purchasing on שבת Shabbos was
תוספות Tosafos' question which would have been I think a different issue.
But anyway, to go further, of course, do you take like both,
the whole pair out in the morning, that one that you're going
to use? And then replenish two right away? Or do you take
it out sequentially? Right, it's a good question. But anyways, he is
nice that he at least explains the logic of six. Although if
he's right, it should have more easily said eight to be clearer.
But at least it's a logic of six to keep a constant
rotation with a four-day checking process in place. Though again, the interesting
thing of the פשט pshat of this is we haven't answered our
question which one I give preference to? Do I give preference to
today's מוסף mussaf or tomorrow's תמיד? tamid? There's no way of inferring
from this. Here's a special demand of the תמיד tamid of four
days checking. And again, I do think what is quite fascinating is
the two things that require four days of checking, a lot of
preparation and care, are the most single event that you could ever
get which is the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, right? And the other
hand, you know, the most common and the most regular which is
the תמיד. tamid. I think it's making a statement about that you
need the equal care for these big special events as you need
for the thing that, you know, that you have to do every
single day. Yeah, I was also going to ask that. Because, you
know, let's say, you know, it's either the choice between checking it
for four whole days or not having a תמיד tamid at all,
I would have thought, "Okay, check it. I mean it looks okay
now. You know, why do you need to like...?" Well, that is
also a very good question. Meaning, you know, it's like if you're
checking for a מום, mum, you know, it's sort of like you're
just repeating the process. It's not like you, you know, if you
did a good job the first time, you know, and you did
it one day before and you made sure nothing happened, it's not
going to all of a sudden sprout a new מום mum in
the next day. So in a way, the whole idea of checking
four days is also to sort of say like, "Yes, we know
you've done it, but it's so important, do it again, maybe you
missed something." So again, I think that the real thing there is
underscoring just how important it is and the degree of care. You're
right. In sort of normal הלכתי halachic parameters of what degree you
have to do to ensure something is good, right, do doing a
good job one day is enough, right? But if you're told you
gotta do it today and tomorrow and the day after just to
make sure, then the message obviously is this is really important and
it matters. Right, but I also think like bringing in the תמיד
tamid to begin with is really important. Meaning like I understand that
under ideal circumstances you want to replenish your stock, okay, check four
days, why not, I'm going to have more anyway. But if it
means that like I don't bring a תמיד tamid today because I
don't have enough checked ones, then basically the בית המקדש... Beis Hamikdash...
Well, in a way that's similar to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's point:
better to do it right than... you know, better if you can't
do it right, don't do it at all. But it's still right.
I mean, you know what I mean? Like if you think according
to בן בג בג, Ben Bag Bag, he presumably assumes it's a
real הלכתי halachic requirement he learns from
a
פסוק. pasuk. Yeah. But it only does it for תמיד. Tamid. I
mean, it's not like a concept. He learns from the פסוקים pesukim
from תמיד, Tamid, right? Right. I understand, running an end around from
a פסוק. pasuk.
Okay, let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לא
יקריבו כבש בבוקר, Lo yakrivu keves baboker, so now if you don't
do it in the morning, do it in the afternoon. But Rabbi
Shimon says no, you need both. You need to do only, don't
choose to do only the afternoon.
If you're שוגג shogeg or אנוס, onus, okay, but במזיד bemezid you
cannot do just the afternoon. רבי שמעון וכולה הויא קרבה בין הערביים,
Rabbi Shimon: vechula havya kerva bein ha'arbayim, ושאין מחנכין את המזבח החיצון
אלא בקטורת הסמים. veshein mechanechin et hamizbe'ach hachitzon ela biktoret hasamim. And
then
we go to the other statement of Rabbi Shimon, that if you
only have the afternoon קטורת, ktoret, then you do the full amount,
not the half amount. And then the משנה Mishna goes on to
talk about מחנכין את המזבח. mechanechin et hamizbe'ach. So that sounded like
an independent statement in the משנה, Mishna, אין מחנכין את המזבח, ein
mechanechin et hamizbe'ach, but the גמרא Gemara here sees it as part
of Rabbi Shimon and has a
ש, shin, שאין. she'ein. Whatever that our גרסא? girsa? Rabbi Shimon did
too. כולה קרבה בין הערביים שאין. Kula kerva bein ha'arbayim she'ein. You're
right. So what is the relationship then of doing the full amount
in the afternoon to the fact that you're מחנך mechanech the מזבח
mizbe'ach with the קטורת? ktoret? What's the relationship then to that? So
the גמרא Gemara says חינוך מאן דכר שמיה? chinuch man dchar shmei?
Who is discussing how to inaugurate the מזבח? mizbe'ach? חיסורי מחסרא והכי
קתני. Chisorei mechasra vehachi katani.
So it's missing some words in here. Here's sort of the background,
the context of the statement.
לא הקריבו כבש בבוקר לא יקריבו בין הערביים. Lo hikrivu keves baboker
lo yakrivu bein ha'arbayim. If you didn't do it in the morning,
don't do it in the afternoon. This is Rabbi Shimon's position. במה
דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, now when is, I'm sorry, not Rabbi
Shimon's, this is even the חכמים Chachamim agree there are times when
you don't do it in the afternoon. Why? במה דברים אמורים שלא
נתחנך המזבח, Bamei devarim amurim shelo nitchanech hamizbe'ach, when the altar has
not yet been inaugurated. Because remember the end of the משנה Mishna
says how do you inaugurate the outer altar? With the morning תמיד.
Tamid. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, you know, it's
always a question: does חיסורי מחסרא chisorei mechasra literally mean it, that
we're missing words, or does it mean we're missing context? So here's
how you say if you want to say context, here's what it's
saying. The end of the משנה Mishna makes clear that there's weight
to the תמיד של שחר. Tamid shel shachar. אין מחנכין את המזבח
החיצון אלא בתמיד של שחר. Ein mechanechin et hamizbe'ach hachitzon ela b'Tamid
shel shachar. So the חכמים Chachamim admit that there's a weight to
the תמיד של שחר. Tamid shel shachar. They just, greater than the
afternoon one, that you start with the תמיד של שחר. Tamid shel
shachar. They just don't agree with Rabbi Shimon that that's enough of
a reason to say that if you don't have the morning, you
don't have the afternoon. Okay, but they do agree that that in
principle you have to start with the תמיד של שחר, Tamid shel
shachar, and the proof is how do you, how are you מחנך
mechanech the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Okay. So therefore it's saying like this. So
what it's reading into that context is the חכמים Chachamim would admit
if you haven't inaugurated the מזבח mizbe'ach yet you can't start with
the afternoon one. You have to start with the morning one, and
that's what's really the end of the משנה Mishna says. Okay. שלא
נתחנך, במה דברים אמורים שלא נתחנך המזבח. Shelo nitchanech, bamei devarim amurim
shelo nitchanech hamizbe'ach. So when is it that you need the morning
one? That's if the altar hasn't been inaugurated. אבל נתחנך המזבח, Aval
nitchanech hamizbe'ach, if it's been inaugurated, יקריבו בין הערביים, yakrivu bein ha'arbayim,
then you can bring it in the afternoon. Yes, the morning matters;
it matters to give it to, to sort of inaugurate, it is
the more fundamental and anchor, but if it's already inaugurated, I'm okay
just doing it in the afternoon even though you haven't done the
morning one. And to that Rabbi Shimon says: אמר רבי שמעון אימתי?
Amar Rabbi Shimon eimatai? Ha, when is that true? בזמן שהיו אנוסים
או שוגגים, Bizman shehayu anusim o shogegim, fine, if it wasn't your
fault. אבל אם היו מזידים, Aval im hayu mezidim, if it was
a willful choice, לא יקריבו כבש בבוקר לא יקריבו בין הערביים, lo
yakrivu keves baboker lo yakrivu bein ha'arbayim, and then I am going
to still insist on the importance of the morning one, and if
without the morning you can't do the afternoon. So that's nice and
that's a good read, meaning the discussion of חינוך chinuch at the
end of the משנה Mishna is just a context for showing which
of the two has greater weight. The חכמים Chachamim admit the morning
one has greater weight, but not enough to say that you can't
do the afternoon. Okay, what, אין מחנכין את המזבח? ein mechanechin et
hamizbe'ach? Would they mean like the first time, for the first time?
For like the Maccabean where they reinaugurated? Well, it depends why. If
it was really נפסל nifsal then yes. So it's a question about
whether it was נפסל. nifsal. And they, you know, like a little
chip, and they fixed it, and then you have to do it
again from בין הערביים? bein ha'arbayim? Yes, presumably yes. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, now we get onto the קטורת. ktoret.
So that's good פשט pshat in the discussion of the, of the
תמיד. Tamid. How about the קטורת ktoret part of the
משנה? Mishna? לא הקריבו קטורת בבוקר יקריבו בין הערביים. Lo hikrivu ktoret
baboker yakrivu bein ha'arbayim. However, comes along Rabbi Shimon and Rabbi Shimon
is saying but when it comes to the קטורת, ktoret, there I'll
agree and I'll let it be in the afternoon. It sounds like
that in the משנה; Mishna; it's the next line and Rabbi Shimon
doesn't disagree. Okay, it says if you didn't do it in the
morning you can do the קטורת ktoret in the afternoon and Rabbi
Shimon doesn't disagree. Why? So we're going to see why the afternoon
קטורת ktoret is, you know, is acceptable by itself for Rabbi Shimon
whereas the afternoon תמיד Tamid is not. So let's take a look.
מנהני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where do you get this from? דתנו
רבנן: Detanu rabanan:
את הכבש השני תעשה בין הערביים. et hakeves hasheni ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim.
It says את הכבש האחד תעשה בבוקר ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין
הערביים. et hakeves ha'echad ta'aseh baboker ve'et hakeves hasheini ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim.
So one in the morning, one in the afternoon. שני בין הערביים
ולא ראשון בין הערביים. Sheni bein ha'arbayim velo rishon bein ha'arbayim. So
the second one is in the afternoon, not the first one, which
means if this is the first of the קרבנות korbanot you're doing,
then you can't be doing it as the afternoon. Meaning the only
one it can be is afternoon if it was second, if there
was one that was already done. one in the morning, okay? It
has to be second, it has to be paired with the first
one. ולא ראשון בין הערבים. velo rishon bein ha'arbayim. במה דברים אמורים
שלא נתחנך המזבח, bameh devarim amurim shelo nitchanech hamizbe'ach, but this is
now even though the חכמים Chachamim who disagree with רבי שמעון. Rebbi
Shimon. But remember they say that when you have to inaugurate the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, that's when you have to start with the morning one.
אבל נתחנך המזבח, aval nitchanech hamizbe'ach, once the altar's been inaugurated, אפילו
ראשון בין הערבים afilu rishon bein ha'arbayim even if, right, it's not
because the פסוקים psukim is in שמות Shemot is the first time
the תמיד Tamid was brought. It's actually worth pointing this out that
the תורה, Torah, I don't think we're often as sensitive to the
fact that the תורה Torah refers to
the מזבח mizbe'ach as the
מזבח העולה. mizbach ha'ola. It says
העשויה בהר סיני לריח ניחוח אשה להשם, hasuya behar sinai lere'ach nichoach
isheh lashem, right? But when it speaks about the תמיד, Tamid, it
says that
first of all, it's always the מזבח העולה, mizbach ha'ola, right? Why
is it always the מזבח העולה? mizbach ha'ola? And then when it
talks about the מוספים, Musafim, let's say when it talks about the
מוסף של שבת, Musaf shel Shabbat, what does it say about the
מוסף של שבת Musaf shel Shabbat in פינחס? Pinchas? I think there's
like a nice example of this where it says,
no, there it just says על עולת התמיד. al olat hatamid. In
שמות Shemot maybe? In תצוה Tetzaveh or something like that?
Where does it say העשויה בהר סיני לריח ניחוח אשה להשם? hasuya
behar sinai lere'ach nichoach isheh lashem? That's surely, that's in פינחס. Pinchas.
פינחס Pinchas ונסכו... veniskay...
By the עולה olah itself, right, by the תמיד Tamid itself. It
says by the תמיד Tamid in פינחס Pinchas it says...
where is it? Does it say that? Yeah, on six, on
כ"ח, chaf chet, עולת תמיד העשויה בהר סיני לריח ניחוח אשה להשם.
olat tamid hasuya behar sinai lere'ach nichoach isheh lashem. What's it mean
העשויה בהר סיני? hasuya behar sinai? Right? And the מזבח mizbe'ach is
always referred to as the מזבח העולה. mizbach ha'ola. And it says
again,
I don't have all the פסוקים psukim right now in my head,
but basically if you look carefully, there's a very strong association with
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the תמיד, Tamid, and it's the מזבח העולה, mizbach
ha'ola, and the תמיד Tamid is associated with the first קרבן korban
that they bring at הר סיני. Har Sinai. And that's going back
to the very way in which the מזבח mizbe'ach was inaugurated, which
these פסוקים psukim are relating to. Why the חכמים Chachamim are able
to say like Michael asked, who told them that it's only that
you only need the תמיד של שחר Tamid shel shachar for the
inauguration? Maybe you always need the תמיד של שחר Tamid shel shachar
because the פסוקים psukim are the first thing it says to do
when you inaugurate the מזבח. mizbe'ach. What do the פסוקים psukim say
here in כ"ט? chaf tet? It says... you're already ahead of me,
Michael... it says in ל"ח, lamed chet, thank you, וזה אשר תעשה
על המזבח, vezeh asher ta'aseh al hamizbe'ach, כבשים בני שנה שנים ליום
תמיד, kvashim bnei shana shnayim layom tamid, את הכבש האחד תעשה בבקר
ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים, et hakeves ha'echad ta'aseh baboker ve'et
hakeves hasheni ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim, blah blah blah... עולת תמיד לדורותיכם פתח
אהל מועד אשר אוועד לכם שמה, olat tamid ledoroteichem petach ohel mo'ed
asher iva'ed lachem shama, ונועדתי לך שם vno'adeti lach sham והקדשתי ושכנתי
וידעו כי אני השם. vehidachti veshachanti veyadu ki ani hashem. So here
it sort of talks about... so you could read this as just
talking about here's going to be the regular thing you're going to
do on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But it's also implicitly saying here's now,
you know, here's how you start doing it. This is the first
thing to do. It's the regular thing to do but it's the
first thing to do. So the חכמים Chachamim are reading this as
the requirement of pairing them, of having the morning, starting with the
morning is only for the חינוך chinuch of the מזבח mizbe'ach and
not for every single day afterwards. So why do we have it
twice? What? So why do we need it twice, once here and
then? Oh, that's a תנ"ך... Tanach... I mean, the קרבנות korbanot are
always repeated, like פינחס, Pinchas, אמור, Emor, I'm not going to have
that discussion now. No, because I would have said that like, you
know, you have it here once, morning and night to show that
when you inaugurate, and then again in פינחס Pinchas when it's already
going, morning and night, to teach you that no matter what, it
always has to be morning and night. Right, well, that's basically רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon's position. Okay, I don't know, I mean but in
general things are repeated in פינחס, Pinchas, so you can't actually prove
it from there. So let's take a look. But I think the
important thing to get from the חכמים, Chachamim, which we often do
lose sight of, is that not only is the תמיד Tamid regular,
but that is also the מזבח mizbe'ach becomes really identified with the
תמיד. Tamid. It's מזבח העולה, mizbach ha'ola, okay? And it's also very
identified as this is the way it started, העשויה בהר סיני. hasuya
behar sinai. So that's the חכמים Chachamim's position and therefore they're saying
that yes, you have to start with the morning one, but that's
in inaugurating it. Okay, so...
I mean by the way that's also the beginning of צו, Tzav,
right? What's the beginning of צו? Tzav? צו Tzav is, you know,
is the very first focus of צו Tzav is about the עולה
olah as well. Does it use the phrase there מזבח העולה? mizbach
ha'ola? Let's just take one last quick look there. It says תורת
העולה. torat ha'olah. והרים את הדשן אשר תאכל האש את העולה על
המזבח. veherim et hadeshen asher tochal ha'esh et ha'olah al hamizbe'ach. I
mean
but it's all about taking the ashes from the עולה olah that's
been burning the whole morning.
Right. I mean so it is very much though focusing on the
removing of ashes, I mean a lot of things could have been
burned there, but again it's with the emphasis of the עולה. olah.
So there really is that very, very strong identification. Okay, so let's
take... אבל נתחנך המזבח אפילו ראשון בין הערבים. aval nitchanech hamizbe'ach afilu
rishon bein ha'arbayim. בין הערביים. bein ha'arbayim. Yeah, I think he tries
to address it. Okay, well let's first read a little more in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that's the חכמים. Chachamim. So אבל נתחנך
המזבח Aval nischanach hamizbeiach once it's inaugurated, then you can do even
starting in the afternoon, אפילו ראשון בין הערביים. afilu rishon bein ha'arbayim.
אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, so Rabbi Shimon says, אימתי, eimatai,
when is this true? בזמן שהיו אנוסים או שוגגים. bizman shehayu anusim
o shogegim. אבל היו מזידים, Aval hayu mezidim, that's okay, I accept
that once it's inaugurated you can do just the afternoon if it
wasn't your fault. But if it was willful, לא הקריבו בבוקר לא
יקריבו בין הערביים. lo hikrivu baboker lo yakrivu bein ha'arbayim. לא הקטירו
קטורת
בבוקר, Lo hiktiru ketoret baboker, but קטורת ketoret is different, יקטירו בין
הערביים, yaktiru bein ha'arbayim, you can do it in the afternoon. Now
here's the issue with Reb Shimon. Since he's saying that there's a
difference between שוגג shogeg and מזיד, mezid, it's very hard to have
him have a principled position. Meaning, if he says that things have
to be paired, you do it right or you don't do it
at all, then who cares about שוגג shogeg versus מזיד? mezid? Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to say since he's making a
difference between שוגג shogeg and מזיד, mezid, for him it's going to
just be a rabbinic concern and not a real sort of principled
issue about whether the thing has to come as a pair or
not, and that's going to allow us to explain the difference between
why we allow the תמיד tamid to be just the afternoon and
not the קטורת. ketoret. So let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says like this, לא הקריבו כבש בבוקר יקריבו, לא
הקריבו בין הערביים, lo hikrivu keves baboker yakrivu, lo hikrivu bein ha'arbayim,
לא הקטירו קטורת בבוקר, lo hiktiru ketoret baboker, that I'll allow you,
יקטירו בין הערביים. yaktiru bein ha'arbayim. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי
כהנים חטאו מזבח בטל? vechi kohanim chatu mizbeiach batel? So I think
this was similar to a question Michael asked before. So if Rabbi
Shimon is really a rabbinic concern of not wanting כהנים kohanim to
do wrong things and therefore not letting them just let it slide
and do it in the afternoon, so just cause the כהנים kohanim
did something wrong the מזבח mizbeiach is going to suffer? We're not
going to have a תמיד tamid at all today just because they
did something wrong in the morning? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, here
Rava says, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's what it means. לא הקריבו
הם אבל אחרים יקריבו. lo hikrivu heim aval acherim yakrivu. So well
that's a different, if you didn't bring the תמיד tamid in the
morning, you're not entitled, you, whatever כהנים kohanim were sloppy this morning,
you're not entitled to bring it in the afternoon, but we'll get
other כהנים kohanim to bring it.
Right, meaning it's not that actually the system isn't happening, the תמיד
tamid the system is happening, it's just you're not entitled if you
were sloppy this morning, you're not entitled to go ahead and do
it this afternoon. So the גמרא Gemara says, so wait a minute,
so why is... no, the חכמים Chachamim don't agree, but this is
his own sort of rabbinic thing. Okay, so right. So now why
is the קטורת ketoret different? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא הקטירו
קטורת בבוקר יקריבו, יקטירו בין הערביים. lo hiktiru ketoret baboker yaktiru, yaktiru
bein ha'arbayim. Why? דכיון דלא שכיחי ומעשרה, dechivan dela shechichi u'ma'ashra, since
the קטורת ketoret is not common. And what does it mean not
common? You do it every single day.
But it means it's not... it's very rare for a כהן kohen
to have an opportunity to do the קטורת, ketoret, only one כהן
kohen did it. The כהנים kohanim that were involved in the עולה
olah in the morning, you had like thirteen כהנים kohanim bringing it
up to the מזבח. mizbeiach. The קטורת ketoret was very special. And
why also was it special? Because ומעשרה, u'ma'ashra, it made you rich.
There was a belief that to bring up the קטורת ketoret made
you rich. So here it was, it's very rare that you get
an opportunity to bring it and it makes you rich, so we
don't have to make גזירות gezeirot that they're going to be sloppy
in the morning and therefore we're going to punish them in the
afternoon if they were sloppy in the morning because if it happened
it would be extremely rare that they wouldn't do it in the
morning and if so there's no need to make some special protection.
Okay, so therefore חביבה להו ולא פשעי, chaviva lehu velo pashei, they
will not be negligent. What's also by the way interesting is that
the גמרא Gemara until now Rabbi Shimon has been talking about מזיד
mezid and now the גמרא Gemara has switched it because since it's
understanding him as a fine and as something rabbinic, it switched it
to not מזיד mezid but פושע, poshei'a, negligent. Okay, so that's basically,
I see everybody's leaving, so I guess we'll wrap up here. Okay,
well maybe I don't know, maybe we'll try to read a little
more. But anyway, so that's what... so the גמרא Gemara in the
end says that Rabbi Shimon's position is not a principled position that
you need both, that's only when it comes to being חינוך chinuch
you need to start with the one in the morning, but it's
really a position about being safeguarding it. And again tying into the
theme before we said which we said before about the checking of
the sheep before days, what needs more safeguarding is the תמיד tamid
which is every single day and therefore people will get sloppy about,
and what needs a lot less safeguarding is the קטורת ketoret which
might also be every day but for you the כהן kohen you
have much less opportunity for it and therefore it doesn't need protecting.
So again it's this theme about the things that are very regular
maybe are the things that דוקא davka need חיזוק chizuk that you
continue to be very careful about and treat seriously. Okay, but in
the end Rabbi Shimon is not saying the same principled position that
we saw he was. Let's just read a little more. You go
ahead. No, but I think רש״י Rashi tried to explain it, אבל
נתחנך המזבח אפילו ראשון בין הערביים, Aval nischanach hamizbeiach afilu rishon bein
ha'arbayim, as to how the חכמים Chachamim get it. But I'm not
quite getting it, because it... where are you? In kind of
the middle, you
know, what's the דיבור המתחיל? dibur hamaschil? אבל נתחנך המזבח אפילו ראשון
בין הערביים, Aval nischanach hamizbeiach afilu rishon bein ha'arbayim, which is what...
דכתיב בפרשת פנחס, dechitiv beparshas Pinchas, it comes from
some... because it doesn't link them. It does call it השני, hasheini,
but it doesn't say את הכבש האחד ואת הכבש השני. et hakeves
ha'echad ve'et hakeves hasheini. It doesn't? It says את הכבש... No, there's
separate פסוקים. את הכבש האחד תעשה בבוקר et hakeves ha'echad ta'aseh baboker
ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערביים. v'et hakeves hasheni ta'aseh bein ha'arbayim.
Ha, that's a good point, wait a minute, wait a minute, that's
a good point. רש״י Rashi says... ולא מנחת. velo minchat. ומנחת הבקר.
Uminchas Haboker.
One minute, look it says את הכבש תעשה, Es Hakevash Ta'aseh, את
הכבש אחד תעשה בבקר. Es Hakevash Echad Ta'aseh Baboker. What does it
say? את הכבש האחד. Es Hakevash Ha'echad. את הכבש האחד תעשה בבקר
ואת הכבש השני תעשה בין הערבים. Es Hakevash Ha'echad Ta'aseh Baboker Ve'es
Hakevash Hasheini Ta'aseh Bein Ha'arbayim. That is a very good question. Unless
what they're saying is because in תצוה Tetzaveh it says את הכבש
האחד תעשה בבקר Es Hakevash Ha'echad Ta'aseh Baboker and then you have
another פסוק Pasuk that says in תצוה Tetzaveh את הכבש השני תעשה
בין הערבים. Es Hakevash Hasheini Ta'aseh Bein Ha'arbayim. It says
it twice. You're right. I don't get the רש"י Rashi either. Okay
let's read just a little bit more in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
אמר רב שמעון וכולהי סקרבי בין הערבים. Amar Rav Shimon Vechulhay Sakreivei
Bein Ha'arbayim. Now we get to why you bring the full complement
of קטורת Ketoret in the afternoon if you didn't do it in
the morning. שאין מחנכין את מזבח הזהב אלא בקטורת הסמים של בין
הערבים. She'ein Mchanchin Es Mizbe'ach Hazahav Ela Biktores Hasamim Shel Bein Ha'arbayim.
You will notice that that phrase של בין הערבים Shel Bein Ha'arbayim
was not in our משנה. Mishnah. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
that the חינוך Chinuch of the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav is different
than that of the מזבח העולה. Mizbe'ach Ha'olah. The מזבח העולה Mizbe'ach
Ha'olah is the morning.
The מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav is the afternoon קטורת. Ketoret. And since
the afternoon, and that might also explain why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
doesn't have an, not what the גמרא Gemara says, it's a דרבנן,
Derabbanan, it's negligent, it's a protection, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
more okay with doing just the afternoon קטורת Ketoret because the afternoon
קטורת Ketoret is the more fundamental one. How do you know? Because
you only are מחנך Mechanech the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav with the
afternoon קטורת. Ketoret. So let's take a look about how we know
this. והתניא בקטורת הסמים של שחר. Vehatanya Biktores Hasamim Shel Shachar.
No, you do חינוך Chinuch of the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav with
the morning קטורת, Ketoret, not the afternoon. תנאי היא. Tannai Hi. It's
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, not exactly clear where they're getting
it from, but yeah, there's a question whether you give more emphasis
to the morning קטורת Ketoret or the afternoon קטורת. Ketoret. אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. So says אביי. Abaye. מסתברא כמאן דאמר בקטורת הסמים של
בין הערבים. Mistabra K'man D'amar Biktores Hasamim Shel Bein Ha'arbayim. The afternoon
one makes more sense that that's the weightier and that creates the
חינוך. Chinuch. How do you know? דכתיב בבקר בבקר בטיבו
את הנרות יקטירנה. Dechasiv Baboker Baboker Betivo Es Haneros Yaktirena. Every morning.
It's quite interesting. The תורה Torah emphasizes the קטורת Ketoret in the
morning. I mean then it says and in the afternoon, but it
starts by saying בבקר בבקר, Baboker Baboker, every morning when you clean
out the נרות Neros of the, of the מנורה. Menorah. So אי
לאו דעביד הדלקה מאורתא הטבה בצפרא מהיכא. Ei Lav D'avid Hadlaka Me'orta
Hatava B'tzaphra Meheicha. So obviously the only way you could be cleaning
out the morning מנורה Menorah is because you lit them the night
before. Now when you were lighting the מנורה Menorah right the night
before, you were also doing the burning of the קטורת. Ketoret. The
קטורת Ketoret and the מנורה Menorah come together. You burn the קטורת
Ketoret at night when you light the מנורה Menorah at night. You
burn the קטורת Ketoret in the morning when you clean out the
מנורה Menorah in the morning. So אביי Abaye is saying since the
burning of the קטורת Ketoret in the morning relates to the cleaning
out of the מנורה, Menorah, so the starting of the process is
the lighting of the מנורה. Menorah. So since by the מנורה Menorah
the starting of the process is at night and the קטורת Ketoret
is linked to the מנורה, Menorah, so the starting of the process
of the קטורת Ketoret is also at night. You're not convinced right
Michael? Okay, no, neither am I. Okay, so therefore since אי לאו
דעביד הדלקה מאורתא הטבה בצפרא מהיכא. Ei Lav D'avid Hadlaka Me'orta Hatava
B'tzaphra Meheicha. ולמאן דאמר קטורת הסמים של שחר. Uleman D'amar Ketores Hasamim
Shel Shachar. How about if you emphasize the morning as the one
that's the more fundamental? גמר ממזבח העולה. Gmar Mimizbe'ach Ha'olah. Because it
says it's just like the, you know there's something else you do
in the morning and the afternoon. It's the תמיד Tamid that you
do on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. And this is also a מזבח. Mizbe'ach.
One is a מזבח Mizbe'ach for קרבנות, Korbanos, this is a מזבח
Mizbe'ach for incense. מה להלן בתמיד של שחר אף כאן בקטורת הסמים
של שחר. Mah Lehalan B'tamid Shel Shachar Af Kan Biktores Hasamim Shel
Shachar. So the same way the altar outside is about, you know,
is about animals and it's about the morning as the fundamental, this
is about incense and it is also about the morning being the
fundamental. It's just different. There's animals, here's קטורת. Ketoret. So I think
that that also raises an interesting question about sort of how do
you categorize the מזבח הזהב? Mizbe'ach Hazahav? Is it a parallel to
the מזבח העולה? Mizbe'ach Ha'olah? And therefore the מזבח העולה Mizbe'ach Ha'olah
works on a system of morning, afternoon, morning, afternoon. Or is it
in the same category as the other things that are in the,
that are in the, you know, in the מקדש, Mikdash, in the
היכל, Heichal, which is the, which is the מנורה. Menorah. And the
מנורה Menorah system is night, morning, night, morning. So where do you
see the primary allegiance or placement of the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav
is I think part of the question here. Okay, but the interesting
thing which the גמרא Gemara doesn't explore, which seems to be implicit
in רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying
since by the מזבח הזהב Mizbe'ach Hazahav the afternoon is what's more
significant, therefore I will say א, Aleph, I'm okay doing just the
afternoon without the morning and ב, Beis, that is the more significant
and ב, Beis, maybe that's why I would do the full complement
and not half because we can start with our focus on the
afternoon. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.